Guide to the Josiah William Bailey Papers, 1833-1967, bulk 1900-1946 RL.00065
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Senatorial Series, 1930-1946, 436 boxes
  - Labor and Management Subseries, 1931-1946
    1937: Black-Connery Wage and Hour Legislation; John L. Lewis, the CIO, and sit-down strikes.
    1938: Fair Labor Standards Act; wage and hour legislation
    1939: Amendments to the National Labor Relations Act (Wagner Act).
    1940: Smith amendments to the Wagner Act; Barden amendments to wage and hour legislation.
    1941: Strikes versus national defense.
    1942: Strikes versus national defense; forty hour work week.
    1943: Strikes versus national defense; exemption of laborer from conscription.
    1944: Bailey's speech, Let us Face the Issue, on proposal requiring labor unions to file financial information with the Treasury Department; reconversion; Work or Fight Bill.
    1945: Minimum wage legislation; unemployment compensation; Bailey's bill to eliminate royalty payments to unions.
    1946: Minimum wage legislation; Fair Employment Practices Commission; Case Strike Control Bill.
    - Labor & Management, 1930-1933, April (Box 341)
    - Labor & Management, 1933, April-1934, March (Box 342)
    - Labor & Management, 1934, March-June (Box 343)
    - Labor & Management, 1934, June-1935, March (Box 344)
    - Labor & Management, 1935, April-May (Box 345)
    - Labor & Management, 1935, May-1936, June (Box 346)
    - Labor & Management, 1936, July-1937, June (Box 347)
    - Labor & Management, 1937, June-Aug. (Box 348)
    - Labor & Management, 1937, Aug.-1938, Jan. (Box 349)
    - Labor & Management, 1938, Jan.-May (Box 350)
    - Labor & Management, 1938, May-Dec. (Box 351)
    - Labor & Management, 1939, Jan.-April (Box 352)
    - Labor & Management, 1939, May-1940, Feb. (Box 353)
    - Labor & Management, 1940, Feb.-July (Box 354)
    - Labor & Management, 1940, July-1941, May (Box 355)
    - Labor & Management, 1941, June-Nov. (Box 356)
    - Labor & Management, 1941, Nov;-1942, March (Box 357)
    - Labor & Management, 1942, March-April (Box 358)
    - Labor & Management, 1942, April-1943, Jan. (Box 359)
    - Labor & Management, 1943, Jan.-June (Box 360)
    - Labor & Management, 1943, June-1944, Feb. (Box 361)
    - Labor & Management, 1944, Feb.-Aug. (Box 362)
    - Labor & Management, 1944, Aug.-1945, Sept. (Box 363)
    - Labor & Management, 1945, Sept.-Nov. (Box 364)
    - Labor & Management, 1945, Nov.-Dec. (Box 365)
    - Labor & Management, 1945, Dec.-1946, Jan. (Box 366)
    - Labor & Management, 1946, .lan.-Feb. (Box 367)
    - Labor & Management, 1946, Feb.-March (Box 368)
    - Labor & Management, 1946, March-May (Box 369)
    - Labor & Management, 1946, May-Dec., undated (Box 370)
  - Medical Subseries, 1931-1946
    Correspondence and printed material pertaining principally to legislation concerning medical issues. Material during the early 1930's deals with funds for a public health service, local hospitalization of veterans, and legislation on birth control. There is some material concerning food and drug legislation (1935), althougn the major portion is located in its own Food and Drugs section. The bulk of the correspondence of the late 1930's and the 1940's concerns various bills dealing with socialized medicine, including the Wagner-Murray-Dingall Bill (1944-1946). There is also information on legislation for the control of venereal disease, particularly 1938-1939. Other major topics include the Tolan Bill (1941) to include chiropractic services as a benefit for government employees; a dental bill (1942); and funds for the St. Agnes Hospital for Negroes in Raleigh (1943). Material is arranged chronologically by day.
    - Medical, 1930, Aug.-1937, June (Box 371)
    - Medical, 1937, July-1942, June (Box 372)
    - Medical, 1942, July-1944, March (Box 373)
    - Medical, 1944, April-Oct., undated (Box 374)
  - Navy and Marines Subseries, 1931-1946
    Correspondence, telegrams, and printed material concern naval appropriations, shipbuilding, and the development of naval power for national defense. There is material pertaining to the U. S. Maritime Commission, including considerable correspondence with Admiral Emory S. Land. There is also information concerning the Merchant Marine, especially for the 1940's during an investigation by the Commerce Committee of communist influence in the Merchant Marine. Although the bulk of the Maritime Commission and Merchant Marine material is found here, other information is located in the Trade and Cormnerce category of the Commerce section.
    Although a generous sample remains, the following types of material were largely discarded: naval academy applications; applications for officers' candidate school; requests for assistance in obtaining commissions, deferments, or re-assignment; copies of form letters to families of dead, wounded, or missing sailors; and requests for publications.
    The material is arranged chronologically by month.
    - Navy & Marines, 1930, Feb.-1933, May (Box 374)
    - Navy & Marines, 1933, June-1937, May (Box 375)
    - Navy & Marines, 1937, June-1940, Jan. (Box 376)
    - Navy & Marines, 1940, Feb.-1941, June (Box 377)
    - Navy & Marines, 1941, July-1942, June (Box 378)
    - Navy & Marines, 1942, July-1944, May (Box 379)
    - Navy & Marines, 1944, June-1946, Dec., undated (Box 380)
  - Veterans Subseries, 1931-1946
    Correspondence, telegrams, and petitions relate to issues affecting veterans of the U.S. Armed Services. The bulk of: the material is constituent mail either concerning various bills or dealing with individual cases. The major portion of the correspondence during the early 1930's focuses on the Patman Bonus Bills to provide cash payment for soldiers' adjusted compensation certificates. Other issues which appear throughout the correspondence include the location of veterans' hospitals, especially in North Carolina, and individual requests for assistance on claims and disability insurance. Numerous letters requested legislative assistance for Spanish-American War veterans and widows, and scattered letters made similar requests for Civil War veterans and widows. Material is arranged chronologically by month.
    - Veterans, 1930-1931, July (Box 381)
    - Veterans, 1931, July-Nov. (Box 382)
    - Veterans, 1931, Nov.-1932, Feb. (Box 383)
    - Veterans, 1932, Feb.-March (Box 384)
    - Veterans, 1932, April (Box 385)
    - Veterans, 1932, April-June (Box 386)
    - Veterans, 1932, July-Oct. (Box 387)
    - Veterans, 1932, Oct.-1933, Jan. (Box 388)
    - Veterans, 1933, Jan.-March (Box 389)
    - Veterans, 1933, March-June (Box 390)
    - Veterans, 1933, June-Sept. (Box 391)
    - Veterans, 1933, Oct.-1934, Jan. (Box 392)
    - Veterans, 1934, Jan.-March (Box 393)
    - Veterans, 1934, April-Oct. (Box 394)
    - Veterans, 1934, Oct.-1935, April (Box 395)
    - Veterans, 1935, May-Oct. (Box 396)
    - Veterans, 1935, Nov.-1936, May (Box 397)
    - Veterans, 1936, May-1937, Jan. (Box 398)
    - Veterans, 1937, Feb.-June (Box 399)
    - Veterans, 1937, June-1938, Feb. (Box 400)
    - Veterans, 1938, March-1939, Feb. (Box 401)
    - Veterans, 1939, Feb.-1940, Feb. (Box 402)
    - Veterans, 1940, Feb.-Sept. (Box 403)
    - Veterans, 1940, Sept.-1941, Aug. (Box 404)
    - Veterans, 1941, Sept.-1942, May (Box 405)
    - Veterans, 1942, May-1943, March (Box 406)
    - Veterans, 1943, March-1944, March (Box 407)
    - Veterans, 1944, April-1945, Jan. (Box 408)
    - Veterans, 1945, Jan.-July (Box 409)
    - Veterans, 1945, Aug.-1946, Feb. (Box 410)
    - Veterans, 1946, Feb.-1947, undated (Box 411)
  - War Department Subseries, 1931-1946
    Correspondence, telegrams, and printed material concern War Department projects, including contracts and bids. There is also material on military installations, the Army Corps of Engineers, and special problems. Legislation affecting the War Department and the Army is found here, although there is some material in the National Defense section. Other material in this section pertains to inventions, war supplies and surplus, and examples of individuals who sought to fight in World War II.
    Similar types of material were sampled as those in the Navy and Marines category.
    - War Department, 1930, Nov.-1933 (Box 412)
    - War Department, 1934-1937, July (Box 413)
    - War Department, 1937, Aug.-1940, Aug. (Box 414)
    - War Department, 1940, Sept.-1941, June (Box 415)
    - War Department, 1941, June-1942, Feb. (Box 416)
    - War Department, 1942, March-Aug. (Box 417)
    - War Department, 1942, Aug.-1943, April (Box 418)
    - War Department, 1943, May-Nov. (Box 419)
    - War Department, 1943, Nov.-1944, April (Box 420)
    - War Department, 1944, April-1945, Feb. (Box 421)
    - War Department, 1945, Feb.-Aug. (Box 422)
    - War Department, 1945, Sept.-1946, Jan. (Box 423)
    - War Department, 1946, Jan.-June (Box 424)
  - Lend Lease Subseries
    The bulk of the correspondence in this category consists of constituent mail concerning the Lend-Lease Bill to provide aid to Great Britain. Nearly all the letters are concentrated in 1941. Material for other years generally pertains to the establishment of various harbors as lend-lease ports for the shipment of lend-lease goods. Material is arranged chronologically by month.
    - Lend-lease, 1940, Jan.-1941, Jan. (Box 425)
    - Lend-lease, 1941, Feb. (Box 426)
  - National Defense Subseries, 1931-1946
    Correspondence, telegrams statements, speeches, petitions, and printed material pertain to national defense policies of the United States, U. S. involvement in World War II, preparation for war, mobilization, and military policy not directly connected with the War or Navy departments. The major portion ot the material is concentrated in the late 1930's and in the 1940's. Information during the early 1930's generally relates to disarmament, defense appropriations, and the development of various branches of the armed services. With the outbreak of hostilities in Spain in 1936, there is correspondence concerning neutrality and an arms embargo. Most of the material from the beginning of World War II in Europe through the entry of the United States into the war revolves around tile issues of keeping the United States out of a European war, military conscription, and neutrality versus aid to the Allies. Correspondence during the war years relates largely to the prosecution of the war and to the home front. Major topics of concern include conscription and the various draft laws, including age limits, drafting single and married men, and the drafting of women; rationing and shortages; the Office of Price Administration (OPA) and its policies; and the Federal Works Administration. Toward the end of the war, thoughts turn to peacetime conscription and the Universal Military Training Bill, the continuation of the OPA, and the return of servicemen to the United States. The McMahon Bill of 1946 provided for civilian control over atomic research, Material is arranged chronologically by month.
    1932: Disarmament conference; national defense appropriation.
    1933-1935: National defense appropriation for the development of the armed services, including the Navy, the Army Air Corps, and the Army.
    1936: Neutrality Act; Arms Embargo; pamphlet entitled Report of the Proceedings of the Statewide Coordination Meeting of Federal Agencies Operating in North Carolina, War Emergency Act.
    1937: Neutrality.
    1939: Embargo on arms to Spain; U. S. involvement in the European war.
    1940: Conscription; neutrality and aid to the Allies.
    1941: Selective Service, constituent opinion on the of Robert Rice Reynolds (D-N. C.) as chairman of the Senate Committee on Military Affairs; pamphlet entitled The People Look at National Defense.
    1942: Teenage Draft Bill; rationing, especially automobile tires and rubber; Federal Works Administration.
    1943: Drafting of married and unmarried men; rationing, especially gasoline; copies of addresses by Eddie Rickenbacker;; OPA regulations. OPA regulations; selective service; peacetime conscription; National Service Act.
    1945: Continuation of OPA; shortages, especially of fuel oil; Universal Military Training; price controls; Work or Fight Bill.
    1946: Continuation of price controls; petitions for restoration of full power to OPA; Universal Military Training; McMahon Bill for civilian control over atomic research; Terminal Leave Bill.
    - National Defense, 1941, Feb.-March (Box 427)
    - National Defense, 1941, March (Box 428)
    - National Defense, 1941, March-1946 (Box 429)
    - National Defense, 1931-1938, Dec. (Box 430)
    - National Defense, 1939, Jan.-Oct. (Box 431)
    - National Defense, 1939, Oct.-1940, June (Box 432)
    - National Defense, 1940, June (Box 433)
    - National Defense, 1940, June-July (Box 434)
    - National Defense, 1940, July-Aug. (Box 435)
    - National Defense, 1940, Aug.-Nov. (Box 436)
    - National Defense, 1940, Dec.-1941, April (Box 437)
    - National Defense, 1941, April-May (Box 438)
    - National Defense, 1941, June-Oct. (Box 439)
    - National Defense, 1941, Oct.-1942, Feb. (Box 440)
    - National Defense, 1942, Feb.-May (Box 441)
    - National Defense, 1942, May-Aug. (Box 442)
    - National Defense, 1942, Aug.-Oct. (Box 443)
    - National Defense, 1942, Oct.-1943, Jan. (Box 444)
    - National Defense, 1943, Feb.-April (Box 445)
    - National Defense, 1943, May-June (Box 446)
    - National Defense, 1943, June-Sept. (Box 447)
    - National Defense, 1943, Sept.-Dec. (Box 448)
    - National Defense, 1943, Dec.-1944, April (Box 449)
    - National Defense, 1944, April-Aug. (Box 450)
    - National Defense, 1944, Aug.-1945, Jan. (Box 451)
    - National Defense, 1945, Feb.-April (Box 452)
    - National Defense, 1945, April-July (Box 453)
    - National Defense, 1945, Aug.-Oct. (Box 454)
    - National Defense, 1945, Nov.-1946, Jan. (Box 455)
    - National Defense, 1946, Feb.-April (Box 456)
    - National Defense, 1946, April (Box 457)
    - National Defense, 1946, April-June (Box 458)
    - National Defense, 1946, June-Dec. (Box 459)
    - National Defense, undated (Box 460)
  - National Defense-North Carolina, 1940-1946
    Correspondence, telegrams, petitions, and printed material concern national defense affairs as they specifically relate to North Carolina and its citizens. The development of airports in North Carolina for the national defense is an important matter covered in this section. Other important issues concern the Office of Price Administration regulations and commodity shortages specifically as they affect North Carolinians and North Carolina industries.
    Material is arranged chronologically by day.
    - National Defense, N.C., 1933-1941, July (Box 460)
    - National Defense, N.C., 1941, Aug.-1942, May (Box 461)
    - National Defense, N.C., 1942, June-Oct. (Box 462)
    - National Defense, N.C., 1942, Nov.-1946, Aug. (Box 463)
  - Political--North Carolina Subseries, 1931-1946
    Correspondence, telegrams, statements, lists, and printed material relate to politics in North Carolina. There is material pertaining to the Democratic Party in North Carolina, the state and county organizations, state officers, state party platform, and finances. A separate folder located at the end of the section is devoted to the Young Democrats in North Carolina. Also included is information on various state and local contests. One of the most important campaigns covered is the 1932 primary contest between Cameron Morrison and Robert Rice Reynolds for the Democratic Party nomination for United States Senator. After Reynolds's election, correspondence between Bailey and Reynolds discussed the distribution of major patronage positions between the two men. Other correspondence throughout the section also relates to patronage distribution in North Carolina. Individual requests and recommendations for specific patronage positions are located in the Patronage category. Scattered letters include references to election laws and to Negroes in state politics.
    A large portion of this section consists of material pertaining to Bailey's senatorial campaigns in 1936 and 1942, particularly the former. Correspondence from friends and party workers throughout the state analyzed Bailey's strengths and weaknesses, policies, voting record, and prospects, and they also discussed more routine matters such as speaking engagements and finances. Included are numerous lists containing names of precinct chairpersons, county and local officials, Democratic Party officers of local organizations, prominent community citizens, and people who could be of assistance in the campaign.
    Correspondence is arranged chronologically by month. Lists are arranged in part by county; others are devoted entirely to the 1936 campaign.
    - Political, N.C., 1930-1933, April (Box 464)
    - Political, N.C., 1933, May-1936, Jan. (Box 465)
    - Political, N.C., 1936, Feb.-1937 (Box 466)
    - Political, N.C., 1938, Jan.-1942, March (Box 467)
    - Political, N.C., 1942, April-1946, undated; (Counties: Alamance-Craven) (Box 468)
    - Political, N.C. (Counties: Cumberland-Person) (Box 469)
    - Political, N.C., (Counties: Pitt- Yancey); Lists, 1934-1936 (Box 470)
    - Political, N.C., Lists, 1936 (Box 471)
    - Political, N.C., Lists, 1936; Young Democrats (Box 472)
    - Political, N.C., Young Democrats (Box 473)
  - Political--National Subseries, 1931-1946
    Correspondence, telegrams, drafts and copies of speechs, public statements, and printed material deal with politics on the national level. Included in this section is material concerning the National Democratic Party and its policies, organization, and finances. Letters discuss Democratic Party platforms, party leaders, fund raising efforts such as the Jackson Day Dinner, and various groups such as the Young Democrats. Political campaigns, both national and in states other than North Carolina, are also covered. There is information on Roosevelt's presidential campaigns, especially the campaign of 1932. Included is material on Prohibition as an issue in that campaign. Lengthy letters analyzed Democratic prospects for the various campaigns. Correspondence for 1944 referred to the movement to nominate Harry Byrd as the presidential candidate of the Democratic Party. The issue of the limitation of presidential tenure in office appears in the correspondence for 1940, 1944, and 1945.
    There is considerable correspondence between Bailey and other politicians and with North Carolinians concerning Roosevelt's policies and the New Deal, particularly as conservatives became disenchanted with the program. Especially significant is the correspondence for 1937 and 1938 dealing with the Declaration of Principles, also known as the Conservative Manifesto, written principally by Bailey in conjunction with other conservative Democratic senators who opposed Roosevelt's New Deal policies. There is also importent correspondence between Bailey and colleagues Peter Gerry, Harry F. Byrd, and Waltor F. George pertaining to Roosevelt's efforts in the 1938 elections to elect liberal candidates and to purge the Democratic Party of those Democrats standing for re-election who had not supported his policies. The threat of a third party, both by Roosevelt supporters and by a supposed coalition of Southern Democrats and Northern Republicans is also discussed. Scattered lettors refer to the influence of Negroes and organized labor in the Democratic Party and to the Equal Rights Amendment. Letters for 1940 include references to the Hatch Act.
    Located at the end of the section are separate folders on Herbert Hoover, Franklin D. Roosevelt, and Bailey's voting record in the 72nd - 75th Congresses. There are also separate folders on Huey Long containing constituent mail, including letters and clippings from members of the Women's Committee of Louisiana, attacking or supporting Long's program, and folders comprised of constituent mail pertaining to Bailey's verbal attack on the Reverend Charles E. Coughlin on the Senate floor. Material is arranged chronologically by month.
    - Political: National, 1931-1932, Nov. (Box 473)
    - Political: National, 1932, Dec.-1936, April (Box 474)
    - Political: National, 1936, May-1938, Feb. (Box 475)
    - Political: National, 1938, March-Dec. (Box 476)
    - Political: National, 1938-1942, Dec. (Box 477)
    - Political: National, 1943, Jan.-1944, Dec. (Box 478)
    - Political: National, 1945, Jan.-1946, Dec., undated; 72nd-75th Congresses, Bailey's Voting Record; Herbert Hoover; Franklin Delano Roosevelt, 1931-1944 (Box 479)
    - Political: National, Huey Long & Charles Coughlin (Box 480)
  - Post Office Subseries, 1931-1946
    Correspondence and telegrams written principally by constituents pertaining to postal rates, mail service, and legislation affecting postal workers. Bills concern the status of substitutes, rural carriers, special delivery messengers, and star route carriers, particularly relative to Civil Service status; wages and salaries for various classes of postal warkers; work week and overtime pay; and paid furloughs. Other material pertains to postal rates, the development of airmail service, and the use by the Post Office of cotton or jute twine. Material is arranged chronologically by month.
    - Post Office, 1930-1932, May (Box 481)
    - Post Office, 1932, May-Dec. (Box 482)
    - Post Office, 1933, Jan.-July (Box 483)
    - Post Office, 1933, July-1934, Feb. (Box 484)
    - Post Office, 1934, Feb.-May (Box 485)
    - Post Office, 1934, May-1935, Feb. (Box 486)
    - Post Office, 1935, March-Nov. (Box 487)
    - Post Office, 1935, Dec.-1937, March (Box 488)
    - Post Office, 1937, March-1938, April (Box 489)
    - Post Office, 1938, May-1939, May (Box 490)
    - Post Office, 1939, May-1940, Feb. (Box 491)
    - Post Office, 1940, Feb.-1941, Feb. (Box 492)
    - Post Office, 1941, March-Nov. (Box 493)
    - Post Office, 1941, Dec.-1942 (Box 494)
    - Post Office, 1943-1944, April (Box 495)
    - Post Office, 1944, May-1945, May (Box 496)
    - Post Office, 1945, May-1946, March (Box 497)
    - Post Office, 1946, March-Dec., undated (Box 498)
  - Prohibition Subseries, 1931-1946
    Correspondence, telegrams, petitions, statements and printed materical concern prohibition, liquor control bills, legislation related to the advertisement of liquor, and the sale of alcohol near military bases. Material for the carly 1930's pertains principally to the repeal of the 18th Amendment, and includes a number of pamphlets dealing with prohibition. There is also information on various liquor bills, federal and local control of alcohol, and the issue of local option. Thc correspondence for 1938 deals largely with a bill to prevent the advertising of liquor over the radio. Material relating to the War years concerns the Shepperd Bill to prohibit the sale of liquor in and near army camps. Material is arranged chronologically by month.
    - Prohibition, 1930-1932, Sept. (Box 498)
    - Prohibition, 1932, Oct.-1936 (Box 499)
    - Prohibition, 1937-1941, Sept. (Box 500)
    - Prohibition, 1941, July-1942, July (Box 501)
    - Prohibition, 1942, July-Dec. (Box 502)
    - Prohibition, 1943-1946, undated; Printed Material (Box 503)
  - Housing Subseries, 1931-1946